[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
SC radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software hello this is to be as
for software engineering radio in this
episode Randy sharp and I will carry on
talking about social and cultural
aspects of working in the software
industry as we did in episode 208 while
working for Kixeye Google and eBay randy
has gained lots of insights on how
companies can maintain good company
culture and today he will share his
opinions on the topic with us hello
Randy I'm very glad to have you back on
the show nice talking with you Tobias
I'm happy to be back before we start our
today's topic I wanted to ask you
whether you want to add something to our
previous discussion on hiring in the
software industry maybe you have even
changed your mind on some statements you
did and so here would be your chance of
rectifying them no I wouldn't say that
I've changed my mind I still have
believed for years that it's
particularly important to hire well
particularly for engineering positions
hire top engineers but as we discussed
at length you know in our last episode
there's less of an objective definition
of the best engineer in other words
there's no one person who's best for
every possible job but you do need to
find the right match of skills and
interests and abilities to to a
particular culture and a particular
organization and to me that's you know
finding that right fit is is super
important but as we also discussed you
know if you can find the highest
performers you know the highest
performers are about 10 times as taught
as well performing as the lowest
performer so it's very much in your
interest as an organization to hire a
small group of very top performers as
distinct from a very large group of sort
of average of below average performers
and how do you Wade the importance of
skills versus culture fit in the end
sure I think you need both it's not one
of those things where one is more
important than the other but it's
critical to have both you know obviously
it's a you know in order to do your job
as an engineer you need to have the the
skills and the tools and so on to be
able to do that but also you know
there's a well-known idea of the
difficult genius or you know there are
lots of more pejorative phrases for it
but it's not enough to be simply
excellent at your job you also have to
be good at collaborating and also have
to fit well in with the team culture so
I think they're equally important ok and
what about close cultural fits versus
people who try to bring new ideas or new
cultural aspects to a company oh that's
an excellent question yeah let me just
say that in order for somebody to be a
cultural fit I don't think it means they
need to be the same as everybody else
again I'll go back to the analogy of you
don't want to build a factory where
everything is the same you want to build
a symphony where different instruments
or we said a rock band I think last time
yeah I think you want to you know you
don't want to have all guitarists you
don't want to have all percussion you
don't want to have all singers you want
to have a mix of all those things and so
you know if you take an example of a
rock band you know the singer might come
out of a jazz tradition but still you
know is an excellent rock singer and you
know what I mean like people bring their
different skills and interests and
abilities and it's the merging of those
differences together into the team that
I think makes it makes it good so I just
want to be clear that cultural fit very
much does not mean sameness it means
fitting like a puzzle piece you know
where we're not not everybody's the same
shape but it all fits together and makes
this wonderful whole does that make
sense it does definitely but it
basically means that why deciding
whether this person will fit in your
team or not you are very much dependent
on your personal intuition and
experience and hiring people right yeah
absolutely and I think humans are very
good at immediately determining whether
somebody else is
friendly or approachable or I mean we do
this very unconsciously and we do that
in milliseconds so I would listen
carefully to you know if you have a
obviously I think well just be explicit
I think the whole team should interview
pretty much everybody I mean assuming
the team is reason small enough so
that's that's possible but but I believe
that sort of everybody on it and you
hear everybody more or less and listen
carefully to people who say they don't
like the candidate you know there's a
reason for that even if it's hard for
them to articulate so yeah I think that
people are very good at determining
cultural fit friendliness collaboration
very quickly and we should listen to
those things that's what I believe we
have now talked a lot about company
culture without actually saying what it
is would you try to give a definition of
company culture as a term boy it's just
as hard to define a company culture I
think as it would be to define a
national culture or something like that
but I'd put together I'd think of it as
the principles upon which we all behave
together you know there are the unsung
times spoken and often unspoken norms of
behavior right so you know in human
cultures it's about how it's about what
are what are the standards and norms of
people relating to one another and if I
if I apply that to an engineering
organization it's well how do we treat
one another how do we react when things
don't go well how do we react when
things do go well what kind of
collaboration do we have I think all
those things are aspects of culture and
so what I'm what I'm intentionally
excluding from culture are things like
the particular process that we have
whether it's agile or waterfall or
something in between the particular
technologies we use you know so I
wouldn't think of a java culture and
agile culture I think it's um I think
for me
company culture is more kind of
fundamental than that agreed yeah agreed
I think you might have a different I
don't know but I think you might have a
different culture and a plumber company
versus a versus an engineering company
but you know what a lot of the
principles are very much the same I
guess so
yes well at least I hope so do you think
there is good company culture and some
sort of toxic company culture or do you
think that every company has a culture
and this is fix maybe the culture can
change but it doesn't really have an
effect on how the company behaves and
how the company works oh I absolutely
believe that there are there are company
cultures that are more effective and
less effective and I think that I've
spoken about this quite a lot actually
recently at conferences I think that the
cup come the culture of the company has
almost more power than anything else I
mean more influence over the long term
success of the company than just about
anything else that's true it that the
company has you know whether it's
processors like it's easier to change
process and technology and much harder
to change culture so do I believe there
are such things as toxic cultures
absolutely I do and we all know this
from our own from our own experience
right I mean we have companies that
we've we've worked at several companies
we have companies that we enjoyed
working at more than others if we think
in our personal lives you know we are
very groups of friends or parts of our
family sometimes you know that we really
love being with that are energizing and
exciting and fun and then there are
groups of people that we are with where
it becomes depressing and unpleasant and
you know I think that's just as true for
come for companies as it is for anything
else okay and you are talking in the
videos I've seen about monitoring or
measuring the success of your software
and that it is
very important to do it and at the same
time really hard of course and when it
comes down to finding key performance
identifiers or KPIs that show how
successful a game is I think I can
follow this idea but what about KPIs for
a working culture do you think you can
find some sort of numbers or generate
numbers that can show whether a company
culture is good or healthy or even toxic
then on the other end that's a good yeah
that one's a hard that's that's hot it's
even harder to identify and what's
what's a good KPI for software but up
off the top of my head I can think of a
few examples so well let's start with
the business the business metrics of the
company are a good indicator about
whether it's successful and it's be hard
to on you know if the business is doing
well it's hard to unpack whether that's
from the culture or the process or the
technology or the people but a good
indicator that things aren't going well
is when the business isn't but in terms
particularly of culture culture is about
people and so I guess I would say
several things one is one would be
metrics around hiring and retention so
particularly retention as a metric how
easy how easy or difficult it is it is
it to retain people at the company and
then on the flipside how difficult or
easy is it to to hire new people in
particular if it's a great company
culture then people that work there want
to hire their friends do you know what I
mean
and so I don't I wouldn't know how to
assign exact appropriate numbers to this
but one it one indicator might be you
know the rate at which we're hiring
people through reference versus through
you know using a recruiting service or
something like that do you know what I
mean because if it's a great culture mm
the employees are more a more incentive
to go out and you know try to
recruit their friends and be those
friends are more likely to come but then
the other metrics I think that indicate
a bunch about you know culture and
process cut you know and there's hardly
there's not always a bright line there
so one area that you can also look at I
think success is the rate of success of
the projects you know
a toxic culture often and uh where this
isn't a direct relationship but toxic
culture often exhibits itself in being
difficult to having a the organization
it's difficult to do new projects keep
them on track and so on do you know what
I mean because the the a toxic culture
sort of ends up being a drag on the
efficiency of the organization so one
indicator would be around how smoothly
you know the organization develops new
projects and finishes current ones I'm
not sure I express that well but I hope
that makes sense that I think that I
guess I'll think if I've stayed in the
reverse way one indicator of a bad
culture might be that it's hard to get
things done yes of course well sometimes
it takes a lot of insight to actually
get to this result I think but and then
from the outside I think sometimes you
only see the good culture like and I
name them too often but like Google they
have a great company culture at least
everybody is saying this and so you know
this but you don't really know whether
they are deploying their tools quick or
whether there's a lack of performance
and therefore maybe a reason in the
company culture but still from the
inside I would see this KPI is a good
good number referring to your
experiences being an employee without
the power of actually changing certain
circumstances I would like to ask you
how a company can actually develop a
healthy and empowering company culture
and how company culture communicated in
this case
sure so I think the the culture again is
sort of unspoken norms of behavior and
that culture can change by people
behaving differently so let's take a
particular example I think on a very
important part of company culture is
collaborating well so that means working
together with members of your own team
you know working in a friendly and
helpful and collaborative way with
people that are on your same team but
also Inter team collaboration right
collaboration with in with it with
between other teams we trust other teams
to do their jobs we we help them when we
can we have good relationships with them
and so on and you know by contrast lots
of a number of company cultures that are
known to be toxic or have a lot of
backbiting and infighting you know
between between individual team members
individual teams so so what could so
what can an individual do is start
behaving better I mean and that sounds
kind of silly and easy and not enough
but it really is I mean it can start
with just one or several people doing
good work on your own part and trusting
others to do the same you know and I
think that's a long that can be a virus
if you like a good virus that that can
spread itself yeah so yeah exactly so
exactly sorry sorry for interrupting you
Ray I mean you were essentially asking
what could somebody do in the grassroots
and I think that's an example yes
definitely definitely from the a from
the other point of point of view do you
believe in CEOs or HR or city also
whoever being able to implement a great
culture too much like a so called Good
King well so the the thing about one of
the main things about company cultures
is you know companies start small and
they get larger right you know no
company forms at fifty four thousand
people like Google but it's
it starts small and it starts with the
leadership you know so I mean all its
taking the example of of Google which
where I did work and I do genuinely
believe it's a wonderful company culture
particularly for engineers you know it's
not perfect nothing is but it's a it's a
very very welcoming very collaborative
very effective culture overall for lots
of the reasons that we all know and you
know the two the two co-founders Larry
and Sergey when they started you know
this is way earlier than my time but
they clearly thought carefully about
creating a culture of openness of really
strong really strong people of
individual responsibility of autonomy
and they've spoken about this internally
and externally for years and that is
still true you know those those
influences that they started you know
whatever 15 years ago are still there in
the culture today so yes I absolutely do
believe that culture is strongly
influenced from the top and whether the
top is you know the co-founders or the
head of a particular business unit or
something like that I think that's
extremely extremely important and very
insightful question since we are talking
about a 55,000 people company do you
know a way or can you think of a way to
bring together the grassroots and the
big CEOs and to enable both to influence
the culture you know what I mean I do
know what you mean yeah how can
everybody all work together and I mean
in some sense that's almost the
definition of a good culture right is
that is that there's openness and in
some sense ease where everybody is
contributing and in many ways you know
difficult cultures are in many in some
ways defined by how hard it is to get
things done and how hard things are to
change do you know what I mean in an
open culture and again we're using we're
using Google as this example the
founders have a great influence on the
company
obviously more than any other
individuals but but also but what's
great about it is that there's a lot of
autonomy and openness and individuals
can contribute as well so I think
there's I think it doesn't need to be
it's not an either-or if that makes any
sense you know a good culture is one
where everybody's everybody's making it
better just a little bit at a time and
what are you thinking about dividing a
company in countries so to say that you
have Google or in my case
CSC America use a and CSC or Google
Germany and both have a different
culture or do you think the whole
company needs to have the same culture
oh great question
no I think one of the defining
characteristics of a good culture is
that it's accepting of sort of lots of
individuality and autonomy and I mean
let me just I'll give an example Oscars
zero down into an example of you know
engineering organizations that I've run
and then pop up a little bit to a large
company so in a in an or an engineering
organization that served numbered in the
hundreds not in the not in the tens of
thousands the best way I found for to
organize is to have small teams where
people are responsible for fully
responsible for their own little areas
you know three people five people Amazon
has a wonderful term called two pizza
teams where you should never have a team
that's so large that it cannot be fed by
two pizzas and all those two you know
all those individual teams should you
know have their own things that they
build services or products or whatever
and rely on one another through
contracts and so on so now let's pop up
and I think that's an extremely
effective way to run an engineer
organization to get things done
now let's pop up you know several more
orders of magnitude and I think that
same idea applies to a
country-by-country organization of a
large multinational company whether it's
you know Google or eBay or CSC or
whatever
trying to impose a globe a single global
culture I think is is not likely to be
successful because as we all know you
know individual areas around the world
people are different from one another
and what's going to work well in I'm
making this up Singapore is not gonna be
the same as in Vancouver or this or in
Berlin or in you know Madras and there's
nothing wrong with that in fact there's
everything right about that it's the
best way to take advantage of the talent
that week that exists all over the world
is kind of working with the local talent
as opposed to trying to impose some you
know global imperialist culture if that
makes any sense yes when we talk about
two pizza teams and you know having the
the grassroots develop the company
culture what do you think is there in
need of actually communicating the
company culture like we all know those
those PowerPoint slides where the
company culture is introduced and we all
know those websites and webinars and
onboarding things do you actually think
that this is needed or is a just
practice and people working together and
showing the culture by living it so I
that's an excellent question and I think
it's not either/or so I think there's no
one way to communicate the culture but
that it should continue to be
communicated in all those different ways
so let's so a PowerPoint by itself is
not enough a web a web a webinar or an
internal website is not enough but it
continues to reinforce those ideas and
well I've heard and experienced myself
up some cynicism
I'll admit about you know particularly
mission statements and big thing you
know
these very high level principles
of big companies you know we're
engineers we're we're want to be cynical
about such things but you know what they
are very helpful because they even
though they're pithy statements of
intent they're a good Brahma they're a
good guideposts you know so we can so if
somebody is behaving you know if we have
I hope that you know a company culture
we design will have something around
collaboration and something around
autonomy and so on and you know those
principles are good things for people to
be able to point to right and say hey
you know Randy I see that you're not
really behaving in this way maybe I
wonder if there's a more collaborative
way to have you know done the thing that
you that you wanted to do or something
like that I find those things I find
those things valuable but I'll be the
first to say that you know if the only
way that let's say this way if the only
way we can we communicate the company
culture is through powerpoints that HR
writes that's not a very effective
situation you know and I mean that's not
enough by itself I think the true power
comes in living it but the but one way
you can reinforce people living it is by
communicating these kind of generic
principles does that make sense some
minutes ago you were talking about
employees leaving and new developers
coming on board and that leads me to a
question which is is turnover of
employees good or bad and do you want
people to move on if they are not
engaged or not in line with the culture
oh sure yeah I think you know as with
any metric like this you know it's not a
situation you know turn over the hot
often a higher turnover is an indicator
of a problem but zero turnover is
another kind of problem do you know what
I mean so there's a there's an optimal
level of turnover in any organization
right because for lots of I mean there
are lots of reasons why people lots of
good reasons why people decide to leave
a company that have nothing to do with
their job or their call
or whatever okay I'm moving to another
country well great our attic can no
longer work for my current company let's
say you know that's that's a fine reason
for people to leave or frankly they find
you know actually I have a friend from
Google who left to go make chocolate for
a living
you know and I totally admire him so and
there's nothing wrong I mean he makes
wonderful chocolate so you know there's
nothing wrong with with that turnover
that's that's one that felt the overall
society should encourage you know people
like him to go follow his dream and make
chocolate even though he was a wonderful
a wonderful employee at Google anyway so
you know I don't believe that I don't
believe that you're not suggesting this
but I don't believe that zero turnover
is the right goal either and frankly you
know I often use another example that's
kind of funny
fraud in lots of in lots of areas that
you know eBay or finance or whatever
there is actually an optimal amount of
fraud and it's not zero in lots of
situations if fraud is zero it actually
means that there's very that the system
is too closed and tight there's there's
probably a long philosophical discussion
about that but anyway I don't think that
optimal level of turnover is zero okay
interesting example I think I need to
think about it
but I don't know if you can say a number
here or if anyone can say a number but
is there a too much in terms of turnover
beards people simply leaving or people
getting fired so there absolutely is an
optimal number or there is that there is
for sure too much you know and and
that's that's intuitively obvious right
like if if we had a company of a hundred
people and 50 people left every year for
whatever reason like that would be
really difficult to sustain that company
right I've never heard of a company if
it's like that but but yeah there's
absolutely too much but you know
specific numbers are are very much gonna
vary by industry by country by even by
type of job you know there are more
there's more turnover
and I think typically it's understood
that there are more turnover in sort of
customer service type jobs than there
are in other you know just you know
there are different types of jobs that
are there where there's more turnover
and less turnover and yeah but there's
definitely there's definitely a concept
of too much I mean it's sort of
intuitively obvious that there has to be
right yes I hope so at least
yeah right let's imagine a hundred
percent turnover every day you know I
mean that's clearly wrong too
definitely well can you give us an
example of a non successful way of
dealing with employees or toxic or
dysfunctional company cultures sure yeah
there are lots of examples I can think
of one example that I'll give for
engineering is a practice that we had at
eBay actually when I joined I joined
just about ten years ago at eBay and I
was there for six and a half years and
I'll take pains to say straight away
eBay does not do this practice anymore
it's been a long time since they have so
this is this is very much reflective of
eBay as of you know circa 2006 let's say
rather than now so you bei had a
practice that was that we called train
seats and a train seat itself was just a
measure of engineering effort so eBay
released the whole site at the time they
were releasing the whole site every two
weeks so that and that was a train you
know so the train for this two-week
period would you know leave the station
at a particular time and so on and the
idea was that you know features that we
were trying to develop to go on the site
would either be on the train or not okay
so that's the general analogy is that
every two weeks the train leaves and
goes to the site and a train seat was a
clever name for the amount of effort
that an engineer would put in for two
weeks right so it's sort of two engineer
weeks worth of effort and there's so so
far there's nothing wrong but the the
one of the things that was really
difficult engineer and wise when the
culture was the way that that
practice ended up working was that you
know somebody would come product manager
or somebody would come up with an idea
of okay we're gonna build this new
feature great okay so then they'd assign
somebody some Engineer would be assigned
to estimate the effort for that front
for that project that they would scope
it we would say right so all right the
scope for this project is going to be
you know eight train seats in other
words sixteen engineer weeks worth of
work okay so so far so good
but now the problem was that that person
that scoped the work was not gonna do
the work right so the work ended up
being the engineers were sort of treated
like a big pool and so those 16 you know
those eight train seats worth of work
could get assigned to basically eight
random engineers for one two-week period
each or one engineer for eight two-week
periods or for engineers each for
two-week periods and so on so get
assigned in a sort of random way to
engineers and that is the you know that
that part of the culture which treated
the engineers like these sort of
undifferentiated cogs was really
problematic it was problematic from a
personal perspective because it didn't
it treated engineers with literally like
interchangeable fungible pieces of
machinery so that didn't feel good as an
engineer but more importantly for the
output so the person who does who
essentially designed the implementation
of the project right the guy who scoped
it and said and wrote this estimate
didn't implement it so that person you
know even though that person was you
know well-meaning and did it you know
tried to do the best job he or she could
there was no incentive in the in the in
the process for that person to make it
easy or hard or whatever to to build it
and and by contrast the people who were
building the project had no essentially
no say in designing it so the incentives
are completely wrong there nobody really
had an end-to-end view of doing things
properly
and even worse and again this is even
with everybody being well-meaning you
know so let I'm not assuming anybody's
is evil or you know in any way but just
everybody trying to do the best job they
can there's no incentive to do that
there's actual disincentive to do things
properly you know the scoper was always
you know strongly encouraged to make the
estimate as low as possible so but you
know was not actually in the code so
there was no understanding of you know
what the trade-offs would be and so on
but then the word one of the worst
aspects of that so you know engineers
treated like fungible cogs and
essentially randomly assigned to
projects but then they'd be random then
a given engineer would be randomly
assigned to some other project and so
there was no long-term ownership of any
particular part of the codebase right so
all these things were extremely toxic to
the engineering culture and really made
it difficult to get things done in the
long term you know so there was
predictable one of the reasons why this
was designed the pro of it is that it's
predictable in some sense when things
get released but the quality of the
resulting project that gets released and
more importantly the the technical debt
that gets accumulated over and over and
over again and the codebase ended up
slowing eBay down for for a long long
time so I think a much better culture
which I think is where eBay is more now
and certainly you know other companies
like Google and Netflix and Amazon is
the complete opposite of that right so
small teams again that are wholly and
completely responsible for a particular
area again a particular service or a
particular product or a particular tool
and I own it end-to-end and are
responsible for their own roadmaps are
autonomous from one another and are you
sort of get to choose their own tools
and techniques and languages and so on
but are held responsible for the results
of those choices I mean to me and this
is true not just subjectively but
objectively in terms of the output that
kind of culture or that kind of
organization is a much more
active does it make sense it does and
this whole notion of full autonomy for
the teams is something I'm which is
really appealing to me but exciting as
well and not always in a good part
because I think or maybe I've just got
the feeling that you can go a bit too
far in terms of autonomy do you think
that you can go too far or is it just
full autonomy is the best you can get I
you can go too far but that's why I Tana
me needs to be balanced with
responsibility so if you only do
autonomy everybody gets to make their
own choices I mean that's essentially
the definition of Anarchy right so
that's query wrong but starting from the
principle of look individual teams get
to choose their own tools and their own
working environments if we start from
that but then we add to it
and mr. team you're responsible for the
results of those choices right so this
particular that's you know let's take a
particular example this particular team
you know this particular three person by
person team is responsible for building
and maintaining the XYZ service okay
well there are other teams in the
company that are dependent on that XYZ
service so it needs to be it needs to
function well it needs to stay up it
needs to perform well and you know so
from the outside it really shouldn't
matter what technology choices for
example inside you know that team makes
inside that service but what does matter
is the is the outside effects of those
choices right if the system is going
down all the time or it performs poorly
or it's a it's inefficient you know all
those all those things are the
responsibility Earl you know you need to
we need to hold the team accountable for
the results of those choices so I like
to say the way I like to think about it
is I like to give a team of goal rather
than a solution right so you know your
goal
this particular team XYZ service team is
build and maintain and operate the XYZ
service and enhanced it going forward
and so on and you own that thing but you
can you know you get to make your own
choices but you're responsible for the
results of those choices now let me also
say that the other fear that people
might have a legitimate fear that people
might have about granting autonomy to
teams as well gosh what if everybody
chooses an entirely different language
what if everybody chooses a different
development environment a different
editor different you know I mean what if
there's no there's no standardization in
the company that's that's very
inefficient in itself true so that's why
again the responsibility the choice
should be of the team but it should but
the company overall hopefully makes it
easier to choose things that are more
standard than otherwise so for example
I'm totally making this up let's imagine
that my see that you know my sequel is
this is the standard or is is you know
widely used at our company so that means
there's probably lots of tooling lots of
fix expertise lots of help lots of other
services around you know my sequel for
example well great so that it's so that
when I'm spinning up a new service or a
new project it should be easier for me
to choose I shouldn't be forced to use
it if it's not the right fit for it but
but it would be a lot easier but if it
is a good fit or a decent fit it's
easier for me to use that than to go off
and you know invent my own database or
you know use something else does that
make sense so it's more think of think
of standardization as less a mandate
from above and more an encouragement
from below right it's just simply easier
to do things more like other people
because there's so much tooling and
useful stuff around it and and actually
let's think of it the other way if I
make the standard choice if I choose my
sequel and it why isn't it I mean it has
to be easier for me to do that than
something else do you know what I mean
like what's what's the point of this day
if we standardized on my sequel what's
the point of the standard if it's not
easier than the alternative does that
make sense yes it does and sometimes the
standardization is just caused by
licenses and other decisions but not
really making it easier and so this is
really desirable to have a setup like
this in a company I think so and but you
know in what's yeah licenses are a good
example so let's take that into account
you know again I should I as the unlit
see now I'm building the XYZ service in
my team
well I'm responsible for the cost of my
running that you know my building and
running that service so if I use
something where we have a site license
well great you know that's that's a cost
I don't have to bear right but if I go
and you know if for whatever reason I
make a choice to use a different piece
of software that has a different license
that we now have to pay for well that
cost should be I should bear that cost
right and maybe that's the right choice
because it made my productivity so much
better and it was exactly the perfect
choice you know technology choice for
what I needed but I should but that
trade-off should be mine does that make
sense like again it's just autonomy you
know you you're responsible for making
your own choices but you're also
responsible for the results of those
choices the implications of those
choices but but would you introduce
consultants then to the to the actual
teams because I think a team of three or
still five people it's not really
capable of keeping track of the costs
and the requirements and things like
that and then still be able to deliver
their code and their solutions so what
would you think of heaven or do you do
you have some consultants in this
concept of autonomy or some other way of
supporting the teams in these decisions
sure I guess I wouldn't think of it in
terms of consultants as much as well it
let's back up I think that I think the
broader question that you asked is if
we're gonna charge people if we're gonna
make people responsible for their costs
don't we need to make it
for them to know what their costs are
and the answer is absolutely yes right
so I don't it will it would be specific
you know company by company what's the
best way to do that particular thing I
mean obviously in start-up environments
where they're using a bunch of you know
cloud services or external services it's
actually really easy to know what things
cost right because you're getting
charged like directly to the company
credit card or something like that you
know what I mean so but I think the
general the the sort of broader question
behind your question I completely agree
with which is you know if we're gonna
hold everybody responsible for their for
their costs shouldn't we make it easy
but let's flip it the other way and
let's imagine the situation where we
have a team that produces a service but
doesn't know how much it costs I mean
that's kind of a problem too right I
mean overall overall in our company we
need to know you know what benefit you
know
however we denominating we need to know
what benefit we get from the effort that
we put into this thing and we need to
know what cost goes into it right you
know what people cost what technology
costs what license cost and so on yeah
and so in the end it comes down to
letting the team simply decide in the
end and see what comes out of it so it's
a lot of trust that is getting into the
teams absolutely yes right yeah there's
I mean again autonomy and Trust are very
closely related and I think that's the
best way to get better the best I mean
the way to get the best work out of
people the best effort the best effect
is to give people ownership and that
includes you know again like I say the
the the concept of owning something is
both the idea of being able to make
choices that's the autonomy part and the
being responsible for the result of
those choices that's the accountability
part and both of those things need to go
together right and you know for example
if you're if you are autonomous without
being accountable
that's essentially a child yeah right
you just defined a toddler and I you
know I have a I have a seven-year-old I
remember when he was a toddler that's
wonderful but that's not an adult way of
behaving but being but then the flip
side also doesn't work being accountable
without being autonomous right like I
hold you responsible for hitting these
numbers except you have no ability to
influence them well that's wrong too so
the only way it can work is if somebody
both has the autonomy or the power to
make decisions you know and the
accountability right but then in the end
there is a big need of giving feedback
in the ends and have some sort of
feedback loops and recurring meetings
where you say okay look look at the
results and look at the things that have
been done how would you organize this
how would you give feedback in this case
and how would you enable the people to
get better after getting those feedbacks
yeah that's a great question
yes yes implicit and thank you for
making that explicit implicit in the
idea is that there is feedback of some
kind right so that again I produced the
X while I build via and maintain the XYZ
service well I should get some feedback
about whether this is useful well one
obvious way is is anybody using it or
not right I mean in fact that's almost
the best indicator you know like let's
you know if we pop up a higher another
level
let's think of a start up oh I have this
I Wis wonderful piece of technology and
this beautiful beautiful product but
nobody uses it well okay that's useless
I mean that's wonderful thank you for
putting all that effort in but it's
useless and you know same for internal
same for internal services or projects
or whatever so you know the best
indicator is are people using it and you
know more more precisely the feedback is
around are people getting benefit out of
it one way to do it it's not the only
way but one way to do it is that
to have a concept of an internal economy
where what if I'm gonna use your service
I have to pay you in some way right
whether it's real money or fake money or
something like that that's really
fundamentally you know economists would
say that's almost the only way to
ultimately figure out what the value
something has is if somebody's willing
to pay for it but that has to be a real
effort on everybody's part to have this
have this economy but but but it
definitely works I mean that's something
that you know the concept of internal
chargebacks
is for the use of other internal
services is a pretty well-known idea
that's not even just unique to
technology companies but yeah so other I
mean obviously there are many different
ways of getting feedback about whether
the team's work is useful again to me I
think the best ways are the ones that
are objective in or in terms of in you
know in the sense of like are people
actually using it what benefit are they
getting out of it they're I mean
obviously you can do meetings and so on
that would also work but there's kind of
no substitute for actually using it or
not right you know if nobody's using it
we should probably spend the effort on
doing something else like that's okay
doesn't mean people are terrible but
like let's go do something else nobody's
using this thing right yeah you're right
I'd like to move a bit forward away from
company culture it is interesting that
you sometimes promote technical
approaches for non-technical purposes I
think then this is because you are a
technician and you are developer and
sometimes we think like this and great
solutions come out of it and one example
that comes to my mind is that you
introduced so-called dsls
domain-specific languages so that
developers could extend services without
writing actual Scala code basically the
example that you're thinking of is more
of a template idea but you know we
wanted to make it really easy for people
this is a kick side we wanted to make it
easier for people to build new services
so we built something that we call the
chassis like the underbody of a car you
know that you can build lots of
different cars on right and and then the
same team that built that here's another
example of you know autonomy and
ownership like this team did a wonderful
job and really exceeded my expectations
we asked them to build the chassis and
they ended up building that plus a whole
bunch of other tooling around it where
you could start from a very simple you
can start from a very simple template
sort of think of it as a hollowed-out
service right all the external or the
outside stuff is done for you and you
just write the if you like the logic of
the service instead of the boilerplate
to talk to other services or to have
other services talk to you and by using
that template it makes it really easy
for developers to get started with in
with a new one yeah so I mean that is
the technology that is a technology
solution to a technology problem right I
mean the problem that you know a the
problem we defined for ourselves one of
many was it was too difficult you know
we knew that we wanted to build new
services and isolate them from each
other for all the reasons that we know
about why services are good but it was
too hard you know it was taking weeks
and weeks and weeks to build a new
service because of all the boilerplate
that we had you know all the
difficulties around deploying it and
getting it configured and and
integrating it with the rest of the
systems and so on we just thought that
there was it there must be a better way
right anyway so so I guess I would say
this was an extremely useful technical
solution to a problem I call it a
technical problem but I'd love to talk
about I mean I guess in some sense it as
a side effect it has nice other benefits
because it encourages the kind of
organization that I was talking about
where well if it's really easy to build
new build new services it make this
particular technology that we put in
place where each of them is responsible
for one or several related services do
you own I mean so it's it's not so much
that the technology solves an
organizational problem but that
reinforced the organization does that
make sense so that we had small teams
and then we made it easy you made it
that much easier for those small teams
to get that much
more done does that make sense so sort
of a force multiplier or a reinforcement
of of that so I think it all works
together yeah I think this is a great
example because you said in your talk
that other teams didn't have to learn
Scala to be able to use the service and
to extend it and that's why I liked this
idea of heaven ideas out there because
this is just the reason why you have
tear cells to enable people who are not
able to write code in this language to
actually use the library and getting
things done so great solution and I'd
like to apply it some when in the future
for myself
we'll see Wow it is yes Oh check out
check out the github page for Kixeye we
again as I mentioned you know in the
talk that you're referencing it was a
small team at Kixeye that built this
chassis but how they were able to do
what they did and as rapidly as they
were is because they built on you know
they stood on the shoulders of giants so
they built very extensively on the
Netflix open source a whole slew of
Netflix open source projects including
what people will know these words some
of them you know Asgard hystrix ribbon
Eureka anyway so a whole bunch of these
Netflix open source projects that were
around you know Netflix as a micro
services architecture so all these you
know all these projects were individual
components that helped with building mic
restore building and deploying micro
services and we sort of leverage those
and built on top of them and put them
all together if you like for our for our
use and then we open sourced that you
know we open sourced that combination so
yeah check it out on check it out on
github it's pretty neat another aspect
of collaboration is that teams sometimes
need to work really closely on a daily
basis and I've heard of teams that will
actually ask who do you need an addition
to that when they were relocated and
everyone moved to a different location
do you actually think that teams need to
Cole okayed it or is there another
solution and what about multinational
companies and teams yeah great so in my
view so again let's start from the idea
that I strongly believe that the most
effective organizational structure is
small teams where the interface if you
like of that small team to the rest of
the organization is very well defined
right so I build no my team builds the
XYZ service and you can call the XYZ
service in this particular way so just a
very weld and here's what it does very
well-defined interface and I think
that's a good way of building services
right you know you'll hear the service
approach in in those words but it's also
a good way to build organizations
certainly Netflix and Google and Amazon
all and all work that way so colocation
I think within one of those small teams
it's extremely beneficial with all those
people work in the same place right
that's very helpful because you have
very you need to have very kind of high
bandwidth communication with within that
team so everybody so well let's say this
way assuming anybody works in an office
right it's good to have all those teams
work together in the same office you
know I think there are other
organizations that are all everybody's
fully remote lots of great open source
projects that work that way I'm not
going to talk about that those are also
effective ways of organizing but I won't
talk about that so ok so I think within
a team you absolutely need to be
co-located right and I also strongly
believe in the DevOps idea that if you
build it you run it so you know all that
all the people are all the skill sets
that are responsible for you know
building the software or making sure the
software is good quality running with
software etc well I believe should all
be co-located ok but between teams
there's to me there's no strong reason
that they need to be co-located do you
know what I mean and let's let's ask the
question
why would they need to be in other words
why would why would the team building
the XYZ service need to be loco locate
co-located with a client of the XYZ
service something like that well if that
really is necessary it means you didn't
define the interface very well does it
that doesn't make sense what I say
because if you if you need to co-locate
what you're saying is you need to have
extremely high bandwidth collaboration
and that's fine
but what that meant is the interface
that you that you wrote wasn't very
clean like it wasn't clear how to use it
it wasn't simple it would didn't solve
all of a single-prop of a separate
problem so I guess I flip it around
where if you think teams need to be
cooked co-located they really ought to
be the same team and if you have but if
you've defined your you know service
boundaries if you like your team
boundaries or your interfaces
sufficiently cleanly then then sometimes
it actually can even be an advantage for
other teams to be elsewhere right you
know Google has offices all over all
over the world and you know one half I
worked in Google App Engine just as an
example you know one large group of the
of the people who worked on App Engine
we're in San Francisco and you know
another in Mountain View so we're all
close and then another another group
when I was there was in Sydney Australia
and that worked great because the the
Australian guys were responsible for
sort of individual services within
within app engine and then when they
were they would take the pager during
their day time and we were you know the
people in the you know California were
responsible for another set of internal
services and when you can define those
services in a clean way and there's your
well-defined interfaces between them
then you actually don't need to be
talking in person all the time you know
you need to do it regularly but not
constantly that's a good idea but it
kind of destroys this whole subject of
Home Office then so so I was talking
about trying to be careful about you
know if anybody works in an office then
dot-dot-dot
so I think there are two
kinds of organizations that work well
there are organizations where you come
to a physical place which is what I just
described and then there are completely
remote organizations where sort of
everybody works from their home office
and that's an entire that also totally
works
you know I've personally not experienced
it but I have I see it work with lots of
companies that I'm familiar with and so
it clearly works very well you just need
to organize your whole process around
that make it really easy for everybody
to collaborate even if they're not in
the same time zone and not physically
together right and there are lots of
tools that you can use to do that what
is often a challenge is having one team
and again I like tech teams to be small
having one of those small teams divided
where you know some of the people work
in the office and others of the people
are always remote that it's it's nothing
that can't work but that that has
challenges right because again to my
mind there are these two you know
organizational attractors you know like
in the sense of complexity theory and
Laurance and you know strange attractors
like there's an attractor that's around
small teams people co-located in the
same physical space and then there's an
attractor around everybody entirely
remote and again in that everybody
entirely remote situation you're forced
as an organization as a and as a process
to to develop processes where where you
don't have to physically be present at
the same time do you know what I mean
and when you do that that can totally
work but the challenge is when the vast
you know when the majority of the people
are behaving as if you just walk over to
somebody's desk but then there are a few
people who are never on the same
timezone and never physically in the
same place do you only mean like that
that's challenging and again let me also
say that I also strongly believe that
you know I'm talking about people kind
of permanently being remote like
obviously for some period of time you
know a couple of weeks or you know I
need to work from home one or two days a
week I mean that's totally fine right
that's but I'm talking about what's the
normal
what's this kind of default standard way
of the team working together you know as
for me I'm kind of done with my
questions do you have anything to add to
the topic company culture and
collaboration not much although I I
guess what I'd say in closing is I
strongly believe that culture is the
most important thing that you can that
you can you know it's easy it's you know
it's relatively easy to change your
software development processes it's
relatively easy to change the
technologies that you use and the tools
it's very difficult to change your
culture and if the culture is not
working right then no that no amount of
technology or process is going to solve
it and when your culture is working very
very well you know everything else flows
from that
so I guess you know I believe that
culture is really really extremely
important it's the best sentence ever to
finish this episode some questions about
what is going on with your talks and
everything people know that you are
talking on conferences where can someone
see you meet you hear you talk oh great
let's see well I'm going to be speaking
at the Q con San Francisco conference in
November so I hope to see people there I
want to say thank you very much again
for talking to us and to me Randy
it was great show thanks for joining
this interview thank you 2 vs I enjoyed
it very much I also want to thank you
listeners for listening to the episode
we want to know what you think about the
show and/or this topic so please go to
our website and leave a comment or go to
iTunes and write a review it really
helps us produce the content you like
this is to be as cards for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio dotnet to support us you can
advertise su radio by clicking the Digg
reddit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
please see the website to details
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]